{
    "id": "71_Education_5",
    "claim": "Warning: Schoolbooks with biased content on the internal armed conflict are approvedFollow the Refusalist Campaign of Fujimorism. Once again since Congress, the Fuerza Popular (FP) bench pushed for a review of school textbooks and their contents about the time of terrorism, as denounced by the National Coordinator for Human Rights (Cnddhh). According to this organization, the Ministry of Education (Minedu) would be about to approve books of first, second and third high school with biased contents on the period of the internal armed conflict, thus missing the truth and memory of the hundreds of thousands of victims of violence and terror unleashed between the years  and  in Peru. The Cnddh denounced that this would be the result of an agreement signed, in September of the , between the then Minister of Education, Idel Vexler, and the president of the Congress, Fujimorista Luis Galarreta, for the formation of a commission that included figures such as the former vice president of Alberto Fujimori, Francisco Tudela, and the retired vice admiral, involved in the massacre of El Fronton, Luis Giampietri. In this review process, workshops were held in which members of Congress and FP advisers and retired members of the Armed Forces participated, instead of institutions and experts in educational and human rights matters. In this sense, the Cnddh warned that this is a mode of interference of Congress in competences that correspond to the executive branch. The Cnddh held that this is intended to deny the events that occurred, as well as 'the responsibilities of the various actors who committed serious crimes against humanity and subjected the country to fear and terror, including the responsibility of the State itself '. This is the statement of the Cnddhh:SOBER THE MINEDU AND THE SCHOOL TEXTS: EDUCATIONAL POLICIES CANNOT BE DISCOGNIZED IN THE PAST OF THE COUNTRYThe National Coordinator of Human Rights (CNDDHH), as opposed to the proposal of the Ministry of Education (MINEDU) of contents for the teaching of terrorism in Peru in school texts, which are intended to validate and print with extreme speed, points out and alerts citizens as a matter of urgency on the following:. The current Congress of the Republic and its majority have been exerting pressure on the executive and other entities of the State to promote their particular interests, which are harmful to the country and its majority citizens. In this context, it has launched an aggressive campaign aimed at denying a comprehensive view of the period of the internal armed conflict (IAC), as well as the responsibilities of the various actors who committed serious crimes against humanity and subjected the country to fear and terror, including the responsibility of the State itself. ♪ NUMBER ♪. The campaign of negationism has set out to impose through the MINEDU a biased view of the history and facts of the CAI, thus affecting the right to the truth that citizens have, in particular children and adolescents in school education. To this end, the Congress and the MINEDU signed an agreement on 'strengthening civic and democratic education in schools 'on September* NUMBER* and announced the formation of a 'Commission 'for this purpose. Thus opening a dangerous door for Congress to interfere with government powers. ♪ NUMBER ♪. In this orientation, the current management of MINEDU has conducted three () consultation workshops to validate the contents of the school texts, prioritizing the participation of congressmen and advisors of Fuerza Popular and that of retired members of the FFAA. The validation process thus acquires a political character that is imposed on the technical, pedagogical and specialized criteria that must guarantee the right to education. This process also omits clear methodological criteria, as well as the wide participation of specialists in the field. ♪ NUMBER ♪. The country's educational policy must be loyal to our recent history, democratic principles and profound respect for the fundamental rights of individuals. As the United Nations Human Rights Council notes, in its comprehensive strategy to address the conditions conducive to the spread of terrorism, 'effective measures against terrorism and the protection of human rights are not conflicting objectives '. ♪ NUMBER ♪. The right to the truth is a fundamental individual and collective right recognized by our Constitutional Court and the Inter-American Court of Human Rights, which requires States to promote in their policies, including education, objectivity about what happened in the country and what its causes were. In this sense, the MINEDU cannot submit to the pressure of Congress, let alone become complicit in negationism. In view of these considerations, the CNDDHH urges the MINEDU and demands that the Peruvian State promote a broad and open dialogue on the contents and purposes of the above-mentioned school texts, leading to guaranteeing future generations the right to an educational and memory policy that respects democratic principles and the fundamental right to the truth. I'm sorry.",
    "source": "redaccion.lamula.pe",
    "date": "19/06/2018",
    "veracity": 0,
    "claims": [
        {
            "claim": "the State itself Schoolbooks the Ministry of Education (MINEDU) biased strengthening on the National Coordinator for Human Rights (Cnddhh) the responsibility of the State itself the Refusalist Campaign of Fujimorism.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "Who does the Cnddhh stand for?",
                    "answer": "National Coordinator for Human Rights"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What did the Ministry of Education say about the Refusalist Campaign of Fujimorism?",
                    "score": 0.7121,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe said on 19/06/2018 that the State itself Schoolbooks the Ministry of Education ( MINEDU ) biased strengthening on the National Coordinator for Human Rights ( Cnddhh ) the responsibility of the State itself the Refusalist Campaign of Fujimorism|ROOT\tSchoolbooks|nmod\tEducation|pobj\tthat the State itself Schoolbooks the Ministry of Education ( MINEDU ) biased strengthening on the National Coordinator for Human Rights ( Cnddhh ) the responsibility of the State itself the Refusalist Campaign of Fujimorism|ccomp"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What does the National Coordinator for Human Rights stand for?",
                    "score": 0.6179,
                    "answers": "for Human Rights|prep"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What does Cnddhh stand for?",
                    "score": 0.5874,
                    "answers": "Cnddhh|appos"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is Fujimorism?",
                    "score": 0.5838,
                    "answers": "Fujimorism|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is redaccion.lamula.pe?",
                    "score": 0.4171,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe|nsubj"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "Once again since approve , the a review of school textbooks and their contents about the time of terrorism bench The Cnddh the responsibility of the State itself Congress The current Congress of the Republic the Ministry of Education (MINEDU) The current Congress of the Republic , as denounced by school textbooks the State itself school textbooks .",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "What did redaccion.lamula.pe say about the a review of school textbooks and their contents about the time of terrorism bench?",
                    "answer": "Once again since approve"
                },
                {
                    "question": "Who is responsible for the a review of school textbooks and their contents about the time of terrorism bench?",
                    "answer": "The current Congress of the Republic"
                },
                {
                    "question": "Who is responsible for the a review of school textbooks and their contents about the time of terrorism bench?",
                    "answer": "The current Congress of the Republic"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What is the current Congress of the Republic being denounced by school textbooks?",
                    "score": 0.6515,
                    "answers": "as denounced by school textbooks the State itself school textbooks|advcl\tby school textbooks the State itself school textbooks|agent"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the responsibility of the State itself Congress?",
                    "score": 0.5418,
                    "answers": "that Once again since approve , the a review of school textbooks and their contents about the time of terrorism bench The Cnddh the responsibility of the State itself Congress|ccomp\tbench The Cnddh the responsibility of the State itself Congress|npadvmod\tThe Cnddh the responsibility of the State itself Congress|appos\tthe responsibility of the State itself Congress|appos"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the time of terrorism?",
                    "score": 0.5293,
                    "answers": "the time of terrorism|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is redaccion.lamula.pe?",
                    "score": 0.4368,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe|nsubj\tredaccion.lamula.pe said on 19/06/2018 that Once again since approve , the a review of school textbooks and their contents about the time of terrorism bench The Cnddh the responsibility of the State itself Congress The current Congress of the Republic the Ministry of Education ( MINEDU ) The current Congress of the Republic , as denounced by school textbooks the State itself school textbooks|ROOT"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "According to school textbooks , the Ministry of Education (MineduThe Cnddh the State itself third high school with biased contents The current Congress of the Republic and its majority the National Coordinator for Human Rights (Cnddhh) , thus missing the the Congress hundreds of thousands of victims of violence and terror unleashed between the years  and  in Peru.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "What did redaccion.lamula.pe say on 19/06/2018?",
                    "answer": "school textbooks"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "How many victims of violence and terror are there each year in Peru?",
                    "score": 0.4818,
                    "answers": "According to school textbooks|prep\tCnddh|appos\tthe State itself|appos\twith biased contents|prep"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What are the contents of the third high school in Peru?",
                    "score": 0.4763,
                    "answers": "third high school with biased contents|appos"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the current Congress of the Republic and its majority the National Coordinator for Human Rights?",
                    "score": 0.441,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe said on 19/06/2018 that According to school textbooks , the Ministry of Education ( MineduThe Cnddh the State itself third high school with biased contents The current Congress of the Republic and its majority the National Coordinator for Human Rights ( Cnddhh ) , thus missing the the Congress hundreds of thousands of victims of violence and terror unleashed between the years   and   in Peru|ROOT\ton 19/06/2018|prep\tThe current Congress of the Republic and its majority the National Coordinator for Human Rights ( Cnddhh ) , thus missing the the Congress hundreds of thousands of victims of violence and terror unleashed between the years|appos\tthus|advmod\t  and|dep"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is MineduThe Cnddh?",
                    "score": 0.3829,
                    "answers": "that|mark\tschool|compound\t,|punct\tthe|det\tthat According to school textbooks , the Ministry of Education ( MineduThe Cnddh the State itself third high school with biased contents The current Congress of the Republic and its majority the National Coordinator for Human Rights ( Cnddhh ) , thus missing the the Congress hundreds of thousands of victims of violence and terror unleashed between the years|dobj\tof Education|prep\tEducation|pobj\t(|punct\tMineduThe|appos\tthe|det\titself|appos\thigh|amod\tThe|det\tcurrent|amod\tthe|det\tand|cc\tits|poss\tthe|det\tNational|compound\t(|punct\t)|punct\t,|punct\tthe|det\tthe|det\tof|quantmod\tand|cc\tthe|det\tand|cc"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is redaccion.lamula.pe?",
                    "score": 0.3344,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe|nsubj"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "school textbooks denounced that the internal armed conflict would be the the country the Congress the country between the then Minister of Education, Idel Vexler, and the president Fuerza Popular (FP) approve the MINEDU Luis Galarreta, for the formation the MINEDU a The Cnddh that The Cnddh figures such as the former vice president of Alberto Fujimori, Francisco TudelaThe validation process in the massacre of El Fronton, Luis Giampietri.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "What did Luis Galarreta approve for the formation of?",
                    "answer": "the MINEDU"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What did the textbooks say about the internal armed conflict?",
                    "score": 0.6335,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe said on 19/06/2018 that school textbooks denounced that the internal armed conflict would be the the country the Congress the country between the then Minister of Education , Idel Vexler , and the president Fuerza Popular ( FP ) approve the MINEDU Luis Galarreta , for the formation the MINEDU a The Cnddh that The Cnddh figures such as the former vice president of Alberto Fujimori , Francisco TudelaThe validation process in the massacre of El Fronton , Luis Giampietri|ROOT\tschool|compound\tschool textbooks|nsubj\tthat school textbooks denounced that the internal armed conflict would be the the country the Congress the country between the then Minister of Education , Idel Vexler , and the president Fuerza Popular ( FP ) approve the MINEDU Luis Galarreta , for the formation the MINEDU a The Cnddh that The Cnddh figures such as the former vice president of Alberto Fujimori , Francisco TudelaThe validation process in the massacre of El Fronton , Luis Giampietri|ccomp"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What was Luis Galarreta's role in the MINEDU?",
                    "score": 0.6137,
                    "answers": "the country between the then Minister of Education , Idel Vexler , and the president Fuerza Popular ( FP ) approve the MINEDU Luis Galarreta , for the formation the MINEDU a The Cnddh|dep"
                },
                {
                    "question": "Who was involved in the massacre of El Fronton, Luis Giampietri?",
                    "score": 0.5892,
                    "answers": "that The Cnddh figures such as the former vice president of Alberto Fujimori , Francisco TudelaThe validation process in the massacre of El Fronton , Luis Giampietri|dep"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What was the relationship between Luis Galarreta and Alberto Fujimori?",
                    "score": 0.5704,
                    "answers": "vice|compound"
                },
                {
                    "question": "Who was the former vice president of Alberto Fujimori, Luis Giampietri?",
                    "score": 0.5354,
                    "answers": "such as the former vice president of Alberto Fujimori , Francisco TudelaThe validation process in the massacre of El Fronton , Luis Giampietri|prep"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "In Congress , workshops were held in which members of approve and a review of school textbooks and their contents about the time of terrorism advisers and retired members The Cnddh Armed Forces participated, instead The current Congress of the Republic and human rights matters.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "In what event were workshops held in which members of approve and a review of school textbooks and their contents about the time of terrorism advisers and retired members of the Cnddh Armed Forces?",
                    "answer": "Congress"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What was the time of terrorism advisers and retired members The Cnddh Armed Forces?",
                    "score": 0.4959,
                    "answers": "about the time of terrorism advisers and retired members The Cnddh Armed Forces|prep\tthe time of terrorism advisers and retired members The Cnddh Armed Forces|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the current Congress of the Republic and human rights matters?",
                    "score": 0.4162,
                    "answers": "on 19/06/2018|prep\twere|auxpass\tof approve|prep\tapprove|pcomp\tschool|compound\ttheir contents|conj\tof terrorism advisers and retired members The Cnddh Armed Forces|prep\tterrorism advisers and retired members The Cnddh Armed Forces|pobj\tretired|amod\tretired members|conj\tCnddh|compound\tArmed|compound\tinstead|advmod\tthat In Congress , workshops in which members of approve and a review of school textbooks and their contents about the time of terrorism advisers and retired members The Cnddh Armed Forces participated were held , instead The current Congress of the Republic and human rights matters|dobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What was the purpose of the redaccion meeting?",
                    "score": 0.3813,
                    "answers": "workshops in which members of approve and a review of school textbooks and their contents about the time of terrorism advisers and retired members The Cnddh Armed Forces participated|nsubjpass"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is redaccion.lamula.pe?",
                    "score": 0.3106,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe|nsubj\tredaccion.lamula.pe said on 19/06/2018 that In Congress , workshops in which members of approve and a review of school textbooks and their contents about the time of terrorism advisers and retired members The Cnddh Armed Forces participated were held , instead The current Congress of the Republic and human rights matters|ROOT\tthat|mark\tIn Congress|prep\t,|punct\tin which|prep\twhich|pobj\tmembers of approve|acl\tand|cc\ta|det\tmembers of approve and a review of school textbooks and their contents about the time of terrorism advisers and retired members The Cnddh Armed Forces|nsubj\tand|cc\ttheir|poss\tthe|det\tand|cc\tThe|det\t,|punct\tThe|det\tcurrent|amod\tthe|det\tand|cc"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "In this sense, school textbooks warned that The current Congress of the Republic and its majority mode of interference of approve in competences that correspond to the executive The country's .",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "What did textbooks warn about?",
                    "answer": "The current Congress of the Republic and its majority mode of interference of approve in competences that correspond to the executive"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What is the current Congress of the Republic and its majority mode of interference in competences?",
                    "score": 0.5743,
                    "answers": "on 19/06/2018|prep\tschool textbooks|nsubj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the purpose of redaccion.lamula.pe?",
                    "score": 0.3999,
                    "answers": "its|poss"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is redaccion.lamula.pe?",
                    "score": 0.3897,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe|nsubj\tredaccion.lamula.pe said on 19/06/2018 that In this sense , school textbooks warned that The current Congress of the Republic and its majority mode of interference of approve in competences that correspond to the executive The country 's|ROOT\tthat|mark\tIn this sense|prep\tthis|det\tthis sense|pobj\t,|punct\tschool|compound\tthat|mark\tThe|det\tcurrent|amod\tthe|det\tand|cc\tof interference|prep\tinterference|pobj\tof|mark\tthat|nsubj\tthe|det\tThe|det\t's|case"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "The Cnddh The country's that this is intended to deny the events that occurred, as well as 'the responsibilities of the various actors who committed serious crimes against humanity and subjected the country to fear and terror, including the responsibility of the State itself '.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "Who was responsible for the crimes?",
                    "answer": "the State itself"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "Who committed serious crimes against humanity and subjected the country to fear and terror?",
                    "score": 0.6867,
                    "answers": "of the various actors who committed serious crimes against humanity and subjected the country to fear and terror|prep\tthe various actors who committed serious crimes against humanity and subjected the country to fear and terror|pobj\twho committed serious crimes against humanity and subjected the country to fear and terror|relcl"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the responsibility of the state itself?",
                    "score": 0.5618,
                    "answers": "including the responsibility of the State itself|prep\tthe responsibility of the State itself|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the purpose of redaccion?",
                    "score": 0.4947,
                    "answers": "that this is intended to deny the events that occurred , as well as ' the responsibilities of the various actors who committed serious crimes against humanity and subjected the country to fear and terror , including the responsibility of the State itself|ccomp"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is redaccion.lamula.pe?",
                    "score": 0.4347,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe|nsubj"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "This is the statement of the Cnddhh:SOBER THE MINEDU AND THE SCHOOL TEXTS: EDUCATIONAL POLICIES CANNOT BE DISCOGNIZED IN THE PAST OF THE COUNTRYThe National Coordinator of Human Rights (CNDDHH), as opposed to the proposal of the Ministry of Education (MINEDU) of contents for the teaching of terrorism in Peru in school texts, which are intended to validate and print with extreme speed, points out and alerts citizens as a matter of urgency on the following:.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "What does CNDDHH stand for?",
                    "answer": "National Coordinator of Human Rights"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What did the Cnddhh say about the proposal of the Ministry of Education?",
                    "score": 0.7559,
                    "answers": "that This is the statement of the Cnddhh : SOBER THE MINEDU AND THE SCHOOL TEXTS :|ccomp"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the CNDDHH's position on the teaching of terrorism in Peru?",
                    "score": 0.7005,
                    "answers": "urgency|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What does MinEDU stand for?",
                    "score": 0.6771,
                    "answers": ", as opposed to the proposal of the Ministry of Education ( MINEDU ) of contents for the teaching of terrorism in Peru in school texts , which are intended to validate and print with extreme speed , points out and alerts citizens as a matter of urgency on the following :|ROOT"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What does CNDDHH stand for?",
                    "score": 0.677,
                    "answers": "National Coordinator of Human Rights ( CNDDHH )|conj\tof Human Rights|prep\tHuman|compound\tHuman Rights|pobj\tCNDDHH|appos"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What does the CNDDHH stand for?",
                    "score": 0.6675,
                    "answers": "on 19/06/2018|prep\tthat|mark\tThis|nsubj\tthe|det\tof the Cnddhh|prep\tthe|det\tthe Cnddhh|pobj\t:|punct\tSOBER|nmod\tTHE|det\tSOBER THE MINEDU AND THE SCHOOL TEXTS|attr\tAND|cc\tTHE|det\tSCHOOL|compound\tTHE SCHOOL TEXTS|conj\t:|punct\tEDUCATIONAL|amod\tCANNOT|neg\tBE|auxpass\tIN THE PAST OF THE COUNTRYThe|prep\tTHE|det\tTHE PAST OF THE COUNTRYThe|pobj\tOF THE COUNTRYThe|prep\tTHE|det\tTHE COUNTRYThe|pobj\tNational|compound\t(|punct\t)|punct\t,|punct\tas|mark\tthe|det\tof the Ministry of Education ( MINEDU )|prep\tthe|det\tof Education|prep\t(|punct\t)|punct\tthe|det\tof terrorism|prep\tterrorism|pobj\tin Peru|prep\tschool|compound\t,|punct\tare|auxpass\tand|cc\textreme speed|pobj\t,|punct\tand|cc\tcitizens|dobj\tas a matter of urgency|prep\ta|det\ton the following :|prep\tthe|det\tthe following :|pobj\t:|punct"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "The current Congress of the Republic and its majority have been exerting pressure on the executive and other entities of the State to promote their particular interests, which are harmful to the country and its majority citizens.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "Who did the current Congress of the Republic exert pressure on?",
                    "answer": "the executive and other entities of the State"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What has the current Congress of the Republic done to promote their particular interests?",
                    "score": 0.7309,
                    "answers": "that The current Congress of the Republic and its majority have been exerting pressure to promote their particular interests , which are harmful to the country and its majority citizens on the executive and other entities of the State|ccomp\tpressure to promote their particular interests , which are harmful to the country and its majority citizens|dobj\ton the executive and other entities of the State|prep\tto promote their particular interests , which are harmful to the country and its majority citizens|acl"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What does redaccion.lamula.pe do?",
                    "score": 0.5419,
                    "answers": "majority|compound"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is redaccion.lamula.pe?",
                    "score": 0.4163,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe|nsubj\tredaccion.lamula.pe said on 19/06/2018 that The current Congress of the Republic and its majority have been exerting pressure to promote their particular interests , which are harmful to the country and its majority citizens on the executive and other entities of the State|ROOT\ton 19/06/2018|prep\tthat|mark\tThe|det\tcurrent|amod\tof the Republic|prep\tthe|det\tthe Republic|pobj\tand|cc\tits|poss\thave|aux\tbeen|aux\tthe|det\tthe executive and other entities of the State|pobj\tand|cc\tother entities of the State|conj\tof the State|prep\tthe|det\tthe State|pobj\tto|aux\ttheir|poss\tparticular|amod\t,|punct\twhich|nsubj\twhich are harmful to the country and its majority citizens|relcl\tharmful to the country and its majority citizens|acomp\tto the country and its majority citizens|prep\tthe|det\tthe country and its majority citizens|pobj\tand|cc\tits|poss\tits majority citizens|conj"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "In this context, it has launched an aggressive campaign aimed at denying a comprehensive view of the period of the internal armed conflict (IAC), as well as the responsibilities of the various actors who committed serious crimes against humanity and subjected the country to fear and terror, including the responsibility of the State itself.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "Who said on 19/06/2018 that it has launched an aggressive campaign to deny a comprehensive view of the period of the internal armed conflict?",
                    "answer": "redaccion.lamula.pe"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What are the responsibilities of the various actors who committed serious crimes against humanity and subjected the country to fear and terror?",
                    "score": 0.5957,
                    "answers": "as well as|cc\tthe responsibilities of the various actors who committed serious crimes against humanity and subjected the country to fear and terror , including the responsibility of the State itself|conj\tvarious|amod\tserious crimes against humanity|dobj\tagainst humanity|prep\tterror|conj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the purpose of the internal armed conflict (IAC)?",
                    "score": 0.557,
                    "answers": "that In this context , it has launched an aggressive campaign aimed at denying a comprehensive view of the period of the internal armed conflict ( IAC ) , as well as the responsibilities of the various actors who committed serious crimes against humanity and subjected the country to fear and terror , including the responsibility of the State itself|ccomp"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the responsibility of the state itself in regards to the internal armed conflict?",
                    "score": 0.5559,
                    "answers": "fear and terror|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the definition of an internal armed conflict?",
                    "score": 0.5493,
                    "answers": "of the internal armed conflict|prep\tarmed|amod\tthe internal armed conflict|pobj\tIAC|appos"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is redaccion.lamula.pe?",
                    "score": 0.4102,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe|nsubj\tredaccion.lamula.pe said on 19/06/2018 that In this context , it has launched an aggressive campaign aimed at denying a comprehensive view of the period of the internal armed conflict ( IAC ) , as well as the responsibilities of the various actors who committed serious crimes against humanity and subjected the country to fear and terror , including the responsibility of the State itself|ROOT"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "♪ NUMBER ♪.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "When did redaccion.lamula.pe say  NUMBER?",
                    "answer": "19/06/2018"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What is the method used to determine a NUMBER?",
                    "score": 0.6646,
                    "answers": "that ♪ NUMBER|ccomp"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What didlamula.pe say about the letter?",
                    "score": 0.5858,
                    "answers": "that|mark"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the relationship between redaccion.lamula.pe and the NUMBER?",
                    "score": 0.4693,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe said on 19/06/2018 that ♪ NUMBER ♪|ROOT"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is redaccion.lamula.pe?",
                    "score": 0.4271,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe|nsubj\ton 19/06/2018|prep\t♪|punct\t♪|punct"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "The campaign of negationism has set out to impose through the MINEDU a biased view of the history and facts of the CAI, thus affecting the right to the truth that citizens have, in particular children and adolescents in school education.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "Who has a right to the truth that citizens have?",
                    "answer": "children and adolescents"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What does negationism do to the CAI?",
                    "score": 0.6751,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe said on 19/06/2018 that The campaign of negationism has set out to impose through the MINEDU a biased view of the history and facts of the CAI , thus affecting the right to the truth that citizens have , in particular children and adolescents in school education|ROOT\thas|aux"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the CAI policy on negationism?",
                    "score": 0.598,
                    "answers": "that The campaign of negationism has set out to impose through the MINEDU a biased view of the history and facts of the CAI , thus affecting the right to the truth that citizens have , in particular children and adolescents in school education|ccomp"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is negationism?",
                    "score": 0.5707,
                    "answers": "The campaign of negationism|nsubj\tof negationism|prep\tnegationism|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What are the rights of citizens in school education?",
                    "score": 0.5411,
                    "answers": "the right to the truth that citizens have , in particular children and adolescents in school education|dobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the CAI's history and facts?",
                    "score": 0.4994,
                    "answers": "that|mark\tThe|det\tout|prt\tto|aux\tthe|det\ta|det\tbiased|amod\tthe|det\tand|cc\tfacts|conj\tthe|det\t,|punct\tthus|advmod\tthe|det\tthe|det\tthat|dobj\tcitizens|nsubj\t,|punct\tparticular|amod\tand|cc"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "To this end, the Congress and the MINEDU signed an agreement on 'strengthening civic and democratic education in schools 'on September* NUMBER* and announced the formation of a 'Commission 'for this purpose.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "What was the name of the group that was formed for civic and democratic education in schools?",
                    "answer": "'Commission"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What is the purpose of the Commission to Strengthen Education in Schools?",
                    "score": 0.6011,
                    "answers": "an agreement on ' strengthening civic and democratic education in schools '|dobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What did the Congress and the MINEDU sign an agreement on?",
                    "score": 0.5847,
                    "answers": "that To this end , the Congress and the MINEDU signed an agreement on ' strengthening civic and democratic education in schools ' on September * NUMBER * and announced the formation of a ' Commission ' for this purpose|ccomp"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is redaccion.lamula.pe?",
                    "score": 0.3739,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe|nsubj\tredaccion.lamula.pe said on 19/06/2018 that To this end , the Congress and the MINEDU signed an agreement on ' strengthening civic and democratic education in schools ' on September * NUMBER * and announced the formation of a ' Commission ' for this purpose|ROOT"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "Thus opening a dangerous door for Congress to interfere with government powers.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "On what date did redaccion.lamula.pe say that Congress was opening a dangerous door for Congress to interfere with government powers?",
                    "answer": "19/06/2018"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What is the power of congress to interfere with government powers?",
                    "score": 0.7233,
                    "answers": "that Thus opening a dangerous door for Congress to interfere with government powers|ccomp"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What are the limits of government powers?",
                    "score": 0.6223,
                    "answers": "with government powers|prep\tgovernment powers|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is redaccion.lamula.pe?",
                    "score": 0.4395,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe|nsubj\tredaccion.lamula.pe said on 19/06/2018 that Thus opening a dangerous door for Congress to interfere with government powers|ROOT\ton 19/06/2018|prep\tthat|mark\tThus|advmod\ta|det\tdangerous|amod\ta dangerous door for Congress to interfere with government powers|dobj\tfor|mark\tto|aux\tfor Congress to interfere with government powers|advcl\tgovernment|compound"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "♪ NUMBER ♪.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "When did redaccion.lamula.pe say  NUMBER?",
                    "answer": "19/06/2018"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What is the method used to determine a NUMBER?",
                    "score": 0.6646,
                    "answers": "that ♪ NUMBER|ccomp"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What didlamula.pe say about the letter?",
                    "score": 0.5858,
                    "answers": "that|mark"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the relationship between redaccion.lamula.pe and the NUMBER?",
                    "score": 0.4693,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe said on 19/06/2018 that ♪ NUMBER ♪|ROOT"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is redaccion.lamula.pe?",
                    "score": 0.4271,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe|nsubj\ton 19/06/2018|prep\t♪|punct\t♪|punct"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "In this orientation, the current management of MINEDU has conducted three () consultation workshops to validate the contents of the school texts, prioritizing the participation of congressmen and advisors of Fuerza Popular and that of retired members of the FFAA.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "How many consultation workshops did the current management of MINEDU conduct?",
                    "answer": "three"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What did the management of MINEDU do to validate the contents of the school texts?",
                    "score": 0.6611,
                    "answers": "the contents of the school texts|dobj\tthat of retired members of the FFAA|conj\tof retired members of the FFAA|prep\tretired members of the FFAA|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "How many consultation workshops has the current management of MINEDU conducted?",
                    "score": 0.6055,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe said on 19/06/2018 that In this orientation , the current management of MINEDU has conducted three ( ) consultation workshops to validate the contents of the school texts , prioritizing the participation of congressmen and advisors of Fuerza Popular and that of retired members of the FFAA|ROOT\ton 19/06/2018|prep\tIn this orientation|prep\tthis orientation|pobj\tthat In this orientation , the current management of MINEDU has conducted three ( ) consultation workshops to validate the contents of the school texts , prioritizing the participation of congressmen and advisors of Fuerza Popular and that of retired members of the FFAA|ccomp\tto validate the contents of the school texts|advcl"
                },
                {
                    "question": "How many congressmen and advisors of Fuerza Popular participated in the consultation workshops?",
                    "score": 0.5711,
                    "answers": "of congressmen and advisors of Fuerza Popular|prep"
                },
                {
                    "question": "Who is Fuerza Popular?",
                    "score": 0.5288,
                    "answers": "Fuerza|compound"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is redaccion.lamula.pe?",
                    "score": 0.4013,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe|nsubj"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "The validation process thus acquires a political character that is imposed on the technical, pedagogical and specialized criteria that must guarantee the right to education.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "What criteria are imposed on the validation process to guarantee the right to education?",
                    "answer": "technical, pedagogical and specialized criteria"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What criteria must guarantee the right to education?",
                    "score": 0.7416,
                    "answers": "technical , pedagogical and specialized|amod\tpedagogical and specialized|conj\tspecialized|conj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the political character of education?",
                    "score": 0.5985,
                    "answers": "that is imposed on the technical , pedagogical and specialized criteria that must guarantee the right to education|relcl"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is redaccion.lamula.pe?",
                    "score": 0.3979,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe|nsubj\tredaccion.lamula.pe said on 19/06/2018 that The validation process thus acquires a political character that is imposed on the technical , pedagogical and specialized criteria that must guarantee the right to education|ROOT\ton 19/06/2018|prep\tthat|mark\tThe|det\tthus|advmod\ta|det\tthat|nsubjpass\tis|auxpass\tthe|det\t,|punct\tand|cc\tthat|nsubj\tthe|det\tto education|prep\teducation|pobj"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "This process also omits clear methodological criteria, as well as the wide participation of specialists in the field.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "What did redaccion.lamula.pe say omits?",
                    "answer": "wide participation"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What is the number of specialists in the field?",
                    "score": 0.5578,
                    "answers": "of specialists in the field|prep"
                },
                {
                    "question": "How many specialists participate in the field of redaccion.lamula.pe?",
                    "score": 0.4792,
                    "answers": "the wide participation of specialists in the field|conj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What are the criteria for redaccion.lamula.pe?",
                    "score": 0.4537,
                    "answers": "on 19/06/2018|prep\tthat This process also omits clear methodological criteria , as well as the wide participation of specialists in the field|ccomp"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What are the methodological criteria for redaccion.lamula.pe?",
                    "score": 0.4457,
                    "answers": "clear methodological criteria , as well as the wide participation of specialists in the field|dobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the process of redaccion.lamula.pe?",
                    "score": 0.4305,
                    "answers": "This process|nsubj"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "♪ NUMBER ♪.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "When did redaccion.lamula.pe say  NUMBER?",
                    "answer": "19/06/2018"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What is the method used to determine a NUMBER?",
                    "score": 0.6646,
                    "answers": "that ♪ NUMBER|ccomp"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What didlamula.pe say about the letter?",
                    "score": 0.5858,
                    "answers": "that|mark"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the relationship between redaccion.lamula.pe and the NUMBER?",
                    "score": 0.4693,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe said on 19/06/2018 that ♪ NUMBER ♪|ROOT"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is redaccion.lamula.pe?",
                    "score": 0.4271,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe|nsubj\ton 19/06/2018|prep\t♪|punct\t♪|punct"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "The country's educational policy must be loyal to our recent history, democratic principles and profound respect for the fundamental rights of individuals.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "What did redaccion.lamula.pe say about education?",
                    "answer": "democratic principles and profound respect for the fundamental rights of individuals"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What is the country's educational policy?",
                    "score": 0.6735,
                    "answers": "The country 's educational policy|nsubj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the history of the United States education policy?",
                    "score": 0.6655,
                    "answers": "that The country 's educational policy must be loyal to our recent history , democratic principles and profound respect for the fundamental rights of individuals|ccomp"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What does redaccion.lamula.pe mean?",
                    "score": 0.6027,
                    "answers": "The country 's|poss\tloyal to our recent history , democratic principles and profound respect for the fundamental rights of individuals|acomp"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What are the fundamental rights of individuals?",
                    "score": 0.6021,
                    "answers": "the fundamental rights of individuals|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is redaccion.lamula.pe?",
                    "score": 0.4055,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe|nsubj\ton 19/06/2018|prep\tthat|mark\tThe|det\t's|case\teducational|amod\tmust|aux\tto our recent history , democratic principles and profound respect for the fundamental rights of individuals|prep\tour|poss\trecent|amod\t,|punct\tdemocratic|amod\tdemocratic principles and profound respect for the fundamental rights of individuals|conj\tand|cc\tprofound|amod\tprofound respect for the fundamental rights of individuals|conj\tfor the fundamental rights of individuals|prep\tthe|det\tfundamental|amod\tof individuals|prep\tindividuals|pobj"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "As the United Nations Human Rights Council notes, in its comprehensive strategy to address the conditions conducive to the spread of terrorism, 'effective measures against terrorism and the protection of human rights are not conflicting objectives '.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "What did the United Nations Human Rights Council note about effective measures against terrorism and the protection of human rights?",
                    "answer": "conflicting objectives"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What measures are taken against terrorism and the protection of human rights?",
                    "score": 0.836,
                    "answers": "effective|amod"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the United Nations Human Rights Council's stance on terrorism?",
                    "score": 0.7633,
                    "answers": "to address the conditions conducive to the spread of terrorism|acl\tthe conditions conducive to the spread of terrorism|dobj\tconducive to the spread of terrorism|amod\tto the spread of terrorism|prep\tthe spread of terrorism|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What does redaccion.lamula.pe say about terrorism?",
                    "score": 0.7458,
                    "answers": "on 19/06/2018|prep\tof terrorism|prep\tterrorism|pobj\tagainst terrorism|prep\tterrorism|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is redaccion.lamula.pe?",
                    "score": 0.505,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe|nsubj\tredaccion.lamula.pe said on 19/06/2018 that As the United Nations Human Rights Council notes , in its comprehensive strategy to address the conditions conducive to the spread of terrorism , ' effective measures against terrorism and the protection of human rights are not conflicting objectives '|ROOT\tthat|mark\tAs|mark\tthe|det\tUnited|compound\tUnited Nations|compound\tHuman|compound\tHuman Rights|compound\t,|punct\tits|poss\tcomprehensive|amod\tto|aux\tthe|det\tthe|det\t,|punct\t'|punct\tand|cc\tthe|det\thuman|amod\tnot|neg\t'|punct"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "♪ NUMBER ♪.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "When did redaccion.lamula.pe say  NUMBER?",
                    "answer": "19/06/2018"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What is the method used to determine a NUMBER?",
                    "score": 0.6646,
                    "answers": "that ♪ NUMBER|ccomp"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What didlamula.pe say about the letter?",
                    "score": 0.5858,
                    "answers": "that|mark"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the relationship between redaccion.lamula.pe and the NUMBER?",
                    "score": 0.4693,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe said on 19/06/2018 that ♪ NUMBER ♪|ROOT"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is redaccion.lamula.pe?",
                    "score": 0.4271,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe|nsubj\ton 19/06/2018|prep\t♪|punct\t♪|punct"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "The right to the truth is a fundamental individual and collective right recognized by our Constitutional Court and the Inter-American Court of Human Rights, which requires States to promote in their policies, including education, objectivity about what happened in the country and what its causes were.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "What is a fundamental individual and collective right recognized by our Constitutional Court and Inter-American Court of Human Rights?",
                    "answer": "The right to the truth"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What right to the truth is fundamental individual and collective right recognized by our Constitutional Court and the Inter-American Court of Human Rights?",
                    "score": 0.6556,
                    "answers": "the truth|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the purpose of the right to the truth?",
                    "score": 0.5313,
                    "answers": "what its causes were|conj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What does redaccion.lamula.pe say about the right to truth?",
                    "score": 0.5154,
                    "answers": "and|cc\tand|cc\tand|cc"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What does redaccion.lamula.pe mean?",
                    "score": 0.5107,
                    "answers": ",|punct\t,|punct\t,|punct"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is redaccion.lamula.pe?",
                    "score": 0.4018,
                    "answers": "redaccion.lamula.pe|nsubj\tredaccion.lamula.pe said on 19/06/2018 that The right to the truth is a fundamental individual and collective right recognized by our Constitutional Court and the Inter - American Court of Human Rights , which requires States to promote in their policies , including education , objectivity about what happened in the country and what its causes were|ROOT\tthat|mark\tthe|det\ta|det\tthe|det\tAmerican|amod\twhich requires States to promote in their policies , including education , objectivity about what happened in the country and what its causes were|relcl\teducation|pobj\tin the country|prep\tthe|det\tits|poss"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "In this sense, the MINEDU cannot submit to the pressure of Congress, let alone become complicit in negationism.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "Who said that the MINEDU cannot submit to the pressure of Congress?",
                    "answer": "redaccion.lamula.pe"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What pressure does the MINEDU need to submit to?",
                    "score": 0.8393,
                    "answers": "to the pressure of Congress|prep"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What pressure did the MinEDU submit to?",
                    "score": 0.8336,
                    "answers": "the pressure of Congress|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the definition of negationism?",
                    "score": 0.6582,
                    "answers": "that|mark\tthis sense|pobj\tthat In this sense , the MINEDU can not submit to the pressure of Congress , let alone become complicit in negationism|ccomp\tbecome complicit in negationism|dep\tcomplicit in negationism|acomp\tin negationism|prep\tnegationism|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the MINEDU?",
                    "score": 0.5621,
                    "answers": "the MINEDU|nsubj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the relationship between the MINEDU and the pressure of Congress?",
                    "score": 0.5574,
                    "answers": "let alone|advmod"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "In view of these considerations, the CNDDHH urges the MINEDU and demands that the Peruvian State promote a broad and open dialogue on the contents and purposes of the above-mentioned school texts, leading to guaranteeing future generations the right to an educational and memory policy that respects democratic principles and the fundamental right to the truth.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "Along with the fundamental right to the truth, what does the CNDDHH believe should be respected by future generations?",
                    "answer": "democratic principles"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What does the Peruvian State want to do with education and memory policy?",
                    "score": 0.5994,
                    "answers": "demands that the Peruvian State promote a broad and open dialogue on the contents and purposes of the above - mentioned school texts , leading to guaranteeing future generations the right to an educational and memory policy that respects democratic principles and the fundamental right to the truth|conj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What does the CNDDHH want from the MINEDU?",
                    "score": 0.5594,
                    "answers": "that|mark\t,|punct\tthe|det\tthe|det\tthat|mark\tthe|det\tthe|det\tthe|det\t-|punct\t,|punct\tthe|det\tthat|nsubj\tthe|det\tthe|det"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the purpose of the MINEDU policy?",
                    "score": 0.4776,
                    "answers": "memory|conj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What are the democratic principles and the fundamental right to the truth?",
                    "score": 0.4771,
                    "answers": "democratic principles and the fundamental right to the truth|dobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the relationship between the CNDDHH and MINEDU?",
                    "score": 0.4724,
                    "answers": "an|det"
                }
            ]
        }
    ]
}